-==破烂熊乐园倾情奉献==-
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业用途
-==http://www.ragbear.com==-
福尔摩斯探案集 104 孤身骑车人
-=Keepfrds MNHD Team=- 校对: ptrpan
华生      干嘛?
Watson.        Yes.
来看
Watch.
你即将目睹的化学反应
The chemical reaction you are about to witness
会解决约翰・文森特・哈登先生
will solve the mystery concerning the persecution
的迫害事件中的疑点
of Mr. John Vincent Harden.
太好了
Excellent,
那位烟草富翁 我该记笔记吗?
the tobacco millionaire, shall I take notes?
不用 时间宽裕之时我会复述
No, I will dictate in the fullness of time.
有位年轻女士想见你 福尔摩斯先生
There's a young lady wishes to see you, Mr. Holmes.
我现在不方便见客!
This is not a convenient moment!
她是位谈吐得体 货真价实的淑女
She's very well spoken, a genuine lady.
毫无疑问
No doubt.
并且坚持不懈
And persistent, too.
赫德森太太 我也是个坚持不懈的人
Mrs. Hudson, I, too, am extremely persistent,
尤其在工作的时候
especially when I'm working.
是紧急事件 福尔摩斯先生
It is a matter of great urgency, Mr. Holmes,
否则我也不会在星期六晚上打扰你
or I would not be troubling you on a Saturday evening.
或许你该...
Perhaps you could, uh,
稍后再做化学反应 福尔摩斯
delay your chemical reaction, Holmes.
好吧
Very well.
请坐 怎么称呼?
Do sit down, Miss, uh?
维尔莉特・史密斯
Violet Smith.
华生医生
Dr. Watson.
谢谢 赫德森太太
Thank you Mrs. Hudson.
正如我说 一位货真价实的淑女
A genuine lady, I told you.
噢 请坐
Oh, please.
呃 谢谢 我坐那里就可以了
Um, thank you, I'll be quite happy here.
好了 史密斯小姐
Very well, Miss Smith,
你得将你的紧急事件告诉我们
you must tell us your matter of great urgency.
这肯定与你的健康无关
It is obviously not your health.
你热衷于骑车 所以肯定充满活力
So ardent a bicyclist must be full of energy.
是的 我经常骑自行车
Yes, I bicycle a good deal.
鞋底边缘的轻微起毛
Slight roughening on the side of the soles
是与踏板摩擦造成的
caused by the friction of the pedals.
棒极了 华生
Excellent, Watson.
你鞋子上的痕迹
The marks on your shoes.
哦 是的!
Oh, yes!
即便是去很远的地方
Even if I have to travel a long way,
我也会像今天一样将单车带上火车
I take my bicycle on the train with me as I did today.
请原谅 但这是我的工作
You will excuse me, but it is my business.
果然 我差点犯了个错误
Yes, I nearly fell into the error
以为你是靠打字维生
of supposing you earned a living by typewriting,
但很明显你靠音乐维生
but of course, it is obviously music.
华生 看看勺状的指尖
You will observe, Watson, the spatulate finger ends,
都是两种职业常见的
which is common to both professions.
但她脸上有股灵性
There is a spirituality about the face, however,
打字员所不具备的
which the typewriter does not generate.
这位女士是音乐家
This lady is a musician.
是的 福尔摩斯先生 我教音乐!
Why, yes, Mr. Holmes, I teach music!
从你的脸色推测 你是在乡村教
In the country, I presume, from your complexion.
在法恩罕附近 萨里的边界!
Near Farnham on the borders of Surrey!
请容我解释拜访的原因
But please, let me explain why I am here.
我是独女 父亲在几年前去世了
I am an only child, and my father died some years ago.
他的名字和职业?
His name and profession?
詹姆斯・史密斯
James Smith,
他是旧皇家音乐厅的乐队指挥
he conducted the orchestra at the old Imperial Theater.
啊 旧音乐厅 福尔摩斯
Ah, the old Imperial, Holmes.
是的
Yes.
请继续
Please continue.
我和母亲举目无亲
My mother and I were left without a relation in the world
只有一个叔叔 拉夫・史密斯
except for one uncle, Ralph Smith,
15年前去了非洲
who went to Africa 15 years ago,
之后便杳无音信
and we have not had a word from him since,
尽管我们寄过圣诞卡和照片
despite our Christmas cards and photographs.
福尔摩斯先生 我得告诉你...
Mr. Holmes, I have to tell you that-
我猜你想告诉我
I think you wish to tell me
你和你母亲一贫如洗
that you and your mother are very poor,
却无法掩盖你的优雅 端庄和才华
not withstanding your obvious grace, dignity and talent.
我们曾经很穷
We were very poor.
啊?
Ah.
大约4个月前 在二月份
About four months ago, in February,
我们得知《泰晤士报》上有则寻人启事
we were told there was an advertisement in the Times,
询问我们的下落
inquiring for our whereabouts.
你能想象我们有多激动
You can imagine how excited we were,
以为有人给我们留了笔财产
for we thought that someone had left us a fortune.
我立即去找了
I went at once to the lawyers
报上所登的律师
whose name was given in the paper.
这位是维尔莉特・史密斯
Now, this is Miss Violet Smith.
律师给我引见了两位先生
The solicitor introduced me to two men,
卡拉瑟斯先生和伍德利先生
a Mr. Carruthers and a Mr. Woodley.
他们自南非回来拜访
They were on a visit from South Africa.
我希望能告诉你
I wish I could tell you
你叔叔给你留下一大笔遗产
your uncle left you a vast fortune,
但正如我所说...
but as I said...
他死时贫困交加
He died in extreme poverty.
然而 我不是空手而来
However, I myself am not without means.
我和母亲从未寻求施舍
My mother and I never sought charity.
不 我不是想施舍你们
No, nor do I offer it.
请坐
Please.
我想问你一个问题
I have a question to ask of you.
你叔叔拉夫说你喜爱音乐
Your Uncle Ralph said you were very musical,
你教音乐吗?
Do you teach music?
是的
Yes.
史密斯小姐 我是鳏夫
Miss Smith, I am now a widower
有个10岁的女儿
with a 10-year-old daughter.
小莎拉
Young Sarah.
她需要位音乐老师
She needs a music teacher.
因此 我不是来施舍你们的
So, you see, I do not offer charity.
工作 他想给你份工作!
A job, he wants to give you a job!
你住在伦敦的哪里 卡拉瑟斯先生?
Whereabouts in London do you live, Mr. Carruthers?
我不住伦敦
I don't.
我住在离法恩罕约6英里的萨里
I live about six miles from Farnham, in Surrey,
的奇尔顿农庄里
at Chiltern Grange.
我不能让母亲独居
I couldn't possibly leave my mother on her own.
我每年付你100镑薪水
I will pay you 100 pounds a year.
每年100镑?
A hundred a year?
是的
Yes.
我想大约是市价的两倍
Approximately double the market price, I think.
噢 不止!
Oh, at least!
你接受了 否则现在你不会在这里
Which you obviously accepted, or you wouldn't be here now.
是的
Yes.
我接受了这份工作
I accepted the offer.
卡拉瑟斯先生同意
Mr. Carruthers agreed
我每逢周末回城探望母亲
that I should go home every weekend to my mother in town.
那现在是你回伦敦的周末之一?
So this is one of your weekend visits to London?
没错
It is.
谈谈你在奇尔顿农庄的生活
Tell me about your life at Chiltern Grange.
刚开始 一切都很完美
For a while, it was quite perfect.
每个星期一早晨我搭火车到法恩罕
Every Monday morning I would take the train to Farnham
然后从车站骑车到农庄
and then bicycle from the station to the house.
小女孩名叫莎拉
The little girl's name was Sarah,
她让人非常愉快
and she was delightful,
也是位好学生
as well as being a very good pupil.
有很大进步 莎拉
That was very much better, Sarah.
我能再弹一次吗?
May I try it again?
当然 我们坐在这正是为了如此
Of course, that's why we're here.
卡拉瑟斯先生对我的工作很满意
Mr. Carruthers was appreciative of my work,
而且是位友好周到的主人
and an extremely kind and considerate host.
听起来很美好
Sounds idyllic.
是的
It was.
是什么破坏了这份美好?
What happened to spoil it?
一位访客
A visitor.
伍德利先生
Mr. Woodley.
你怎么猜到的 福尔摩斯先生?
However did you guess, Mr. Holmes?
史密斯小姐 我从不猜测
Miss Smith, I never guess.
谈谈他的来访
Tell me about his visit.
他过来呆一个星期
He arrived and was to stay for a week.
对我来说如同三秋
But to me it seemed like three months.
那可恨的红胡子!
Oh, that odious red mustache!
一天晚饭后
One evening after dinner,
卡拉瑟斯先生要离席片刻
Mr. Carruthers had to leave us for a minute
去门外见一位访客
to see somebody at the door.
有位绅士想见你 先生
A gentleman to see you, sir.
失陪一下
Will you excuse me?
这下可好多了
That's better.
什么好多了?
Better, in what way?
没有老头在这碍手碍脚
It's better to get the old folk out of the way.
我不认为卡拉瑟斯先生老
I don't regard Mr. Carruthers as old.
是啊 但也不如我俩
Oh, yes, but he isn't young...
那般年轻
like us.
我希望你别对着我喷烟 伍德利先生
I do wish you wouldn't blow smoke in my face, Mr. Woodley.
我可不信
Oh, I don't believe that for a moment.
不信什么?
What don't you believe?
当女人说不希望你做什么
When women say they wish you wouldn't do something,
她们通常表里不一
it generally means the exact opposite.
我没有表里不一!
I mean precisely what I say!
伍德利先生 你能不能别烦我?
Mr. Woodley, will you please leave me alone!
不
No.
实话和你说 我会烦着你
To tell you the truth, I won't leave you alone,
直到我说出真心话
not until I've said what's in my heart.
什么意思?
Whatever do you mean?
我不懂繁文缛节
I'm not very well up on the social graces,
但我愿意学 只要你愿意教我
but I'm prepared to learn, if you're prepared to teach me.
这真荒谬!
Oh, this is absurd!
一点也不荒谬 我在跟你求婚!
It isn't absurd! I'm asking you to marry me!
我是诚心诚意的
I mean it, it's from the heart.
钱不是问题
Money isn't a problem,
我在南非混得很好
I did very well out in South Africa.
我可以给你更好的生活
Whatever you are accustomed to, I can give you better,
比你现在的要好
better that you're accustomed to;
珠宝 钻石
jewelry, diamonds.
如果你想要钻石 我可以给你钻石
You want diamonds, oh, I can give you diamonds.
我不要钻石!
I don't want diamonds!
好好考虑一下 我不会催你
Oh, you think about it. I won't rush you.
我已经考虑过了
I've thought about it,
这个想法太可笑了
and the idea is ludicrous.
你不能责怪我的争取!
Well, you can't blame me for trying!
你非常美
You're very beautiful.
为了消除芥蒂
Listen, just to show there are no hard feelings,
让我亲一下吧
what about a little kiss to be going on with, hmm,
就在脸颊轻吻一下
just a peck on the cheek.
伍德利先生 请你住手!
Mr. Woodley, will you please stop it!
我说过女人表里不一
Oh, I told you before about women who say stop it.
不!
No!
越挣扎 越有趣
The more they struggle, the more fun it is.
卡拉瑟斯先生 让他住手!
Mr. Carruthers, will you stop him!
滚出我家!
Get out of this house!
好啊!
All right!
我走
I'm going.
我对老头可没有兴趣
I'm not interested in old men,
还有老处女!
and old maids!
我对刚刚发生的一切
I can only offer you my most sincere apologies
表示深深的歉意
for what has happened.
如果我向你保证这种事再不会发生
If I give you my assurance that it will not happen again,
你能为了我女儿留下来吗?
for my daughter's sake, will you stay?
是的 我会留下来
Yes, I will stay.
谢谢 维尔莉特
Thank you, Violet.
自此之后我再没见过伍德利先生
Mr. Woodley left the house and I have not seen him since.
无赖!
The blackguard!
卡拉瑟斯先生的举止
Has there been any change
有什么改变吗?
in the behavior of Mr. Carruthers?
没有 他一如既往 周到而彬彬有礼
No, he continues to be polite and considerate and courteous.
史密斯小姐 请继续说
Now, Miss Smith, please, please continue.
的确 还有一件事
Yes, there is something else.
也许是我多心
Oh, it may be a mere fancy of mine,
但似乎卡拉瑟斯先生
but it seems to me that Mr. Carruthers
对我有意思
shows a great deal of interest in me.
他什么也没说 他是位很好的绅士
Oh, he has never said anything, he is a perfect gentleman,
但一个姑娘心里总明白
but, a girl always knows.
我相信
So I believe.
而我推定
And I assume
你对此没有予以任何
that these feelings that you sense from Mr. Carruthers
感情上的回报吧?
are not reciprocated?
他是位友好慷慨的雇主
He is a kind and generous employer,
但我已经订婚了
but I am already engaged.
这位幸运的男士是谁?
Oh, the name of this very fortunate young man is?!
西里尔・莫尔顿
Cyril Morton.
他是位电气工程师
He's an electrical engineer
在考文垂的米德兰电气公司工作
with the Midland Electric Company in Coventry.
我们要在夏末结婚
We're to be married at the end of the summer.
祝你幸福
We wish you joy.
谢谢
Thank you.
然而我很困惑你为什么会来找我
Yet, I am puzzled as to why you have chosen to consult me.
你说的事的确引人入胜
It is an intriguing story, to be sure,
但我感觉到你的恐惧 却不知其因
but I sense you are frightened, and do not understand why.
你看来有足够的自我保护能力
You seem well capable of protecting yourself.
求求你 帮帮我 福尔摩斯先生!
Please, help me, Mr. Holmes!
怎么了?
What is it?
我被跟踪了
I am being followed.
被谁跟踪?
Followed, by whom?
一个骑单车的人
A cyclist.
每个星期六早晨
Every Saturday morning
我从农庄骑车到法恩罕车站
I bicycle from the house to Farnham Station
搭12点22分的火车进城
to catch the 12:22 to town.
有段路程人烟稀少
There is one very quiet and lonely stretch of road
路的一旁是查灵顿石南丛
that lies between Charlington Heath on the one hand
另一旁是查灵顿庄园树林
and the woods of Charlington Hall on the other.
两周前的今天 我经过那条路
Two weeks ago today, I was passing this place
偶然回头时 见到一个男人
when I chanced to look back and saw a man,
也骑着自行车
also on a bicycle.
之后星期一回去时也见到他
The following Monday when I returned he was there again.
我明白了
I see.
上个星期六和星期一同样如此
And again last Saturday, and again last Monday.
你有跟你的雇主提过吗?
Have you mentioned this to your employer?
提过
Yes.
卡拉瑟斯先生非常担心
Mr. Carruthers was very concerned,
并订购了马和轻便马车
and has ordered a horse and trap
这样我就不必独自上路
so that in the future I should not travel unaccompanied.
但他们还没到
But they've not yet arrived.
今天早上呢?
And this morning?
他又跟踪我了
He was following me again.
我减速 他也减速
I slowed down, but he did the same.
我停车 他也停车
Then I stopped completely, but he did the same.
因此我心生一计来对付他
So, I laid a trap for him.
这条路上有处急转弯
There is a sharp turning of the road,
我快速转弯
and I pedaled very quickly towards this
然后停车等着
and then stopped and waited.
但他就这么凭空消失了
But he seemed to disappear into thin air.
你能形容一下这名男子吗?
Can you describe this man?
我知道你只远远见过他
I realize that you've only seen him from a distance.
是的
Yes.
他穿着深色外衣 戴着深色眼镜
He wears a dark suit, dark spectacles,
蓄着络腮胡
and he has a beard.
年不年轻?
Young, old?
大概是中年人
He's about middle-aged.
看看我有没有弄错地形
Now, let me see if I have the geography correct.
这是条路 这边有个急弯
Here is the road, with a sharp bend in it here.
这边是查灵顿石南丛
On this side, Charlington Heath,
另一边是查灵顿庄园树林
and on the other, the woods of Charlington Hall.
你在弯道等了他多久?
How long did you wait for him here around the bend?
不超过2分钟
Oh, no more than two minutes.
因此他不可能原路返回
So he could not have retreated back down the road.
周围有岔路吗?
Are there any side roads?
这段路没有
None along this stretch.
会不会是往石南丛小路走了?
Could he have taken a footpath across the heath?
石南丛十分平整荒芜
Oh, the heath is totally flat and bleak.
我想如果那样我能看到他
I think I would have noticed him.
因此 根据排除推理法
So, by a process of exclusion,
得出结论 他走进了
we arrive at the fact that he made his way towards
查灵顿庄园树林
Charlington Hall.
卡拉瑟斯先生如何谋生?
Now how does Mr. Carruthers make his living?
他非常富有
Oh, he's a rich man.
但却没有马车或马
But no carriages or horses.
但起码他非常富裕
Well, at least he's very well off.
他每周进城两三次
He goes into the city two or three times a week,
有时会提起他的金矿股票
and he sometimes refers to his gold shares.
我明白了
Yes, I see.
你必须马上告诉我
You must let me know immediately
任何新发现的情况
if there are any fresh developments.
眼下我非常忙
I am extremely busy just now,
但我会抽空调查你的案子
but I will find time to make inquiries into your case.
谢谢 福尔摩斯先生
Thank you, Mr. Holmes.
与此同时 不要没通知我就采取行动
In the meantime, take no step without letting me know.
我相信我们会给你带来好消息的
I'm sure we shall have nothing but good news for you.
希望如此 华生医生
I do hope so, Dr. Watson.
非常可爱的女孩
Very lovely girl.
是的
Yes.
根据自然规律
And it is part of the settled order of nature
这样的女孩应该不乏追求者
that such a girl should have followers,
不过没人会选荒僻村路骑车追求
but for choice, not on bicycles in lonely country roads.
你真认为她身处险境吗 福尔摩斯?
You really think she may be in some danger, Holmes?
是的
Oh, yes.
接下来的星期一
On the following Monday,
福尔摩斯因为工作
Holmes found that he had business
而逗留伦敦
which detained him in London,
因此他派我搭早班车前往法恩罕
so, he dispatched me on the early train to Farnham
以便观察史密斯小姐
that I might observe Miss Smith's passage
经过查灵顿庄园所走的路
past Charlington Hall.
那里正如她所描述的一般
The setting was just as she had described,
庄园被茂密的树林环绕
heavily wooded on the side bordering the hall,
路的另一边则一片荒芜
and utterly exposed on the other.
我选好唯一的藏身处 等待着
I selected the only available cover, and waited.
华生 你在浪费时间
Watson, you have wasted your time.
我以为我做得很好
I thought I did rather well.
不 你的藏身处选得很糟糕
No, your hiding place was ill-chosen.
你应该藏在
You should have been in the bracken
路另一边的灌木丛中
on the other side of the road.
那样就可以近距离观察
Then that way you would have had a close view
那位迷人的孤身骑车人
of this fascinating solitary cyclist.
谢谢
Thank you.
而你却藏在100码之外
As it is, you were a hundred yards away
能告诉我的情况甚至比
and can tell me even less
上周六史密斯小姐说的还少
than Miss Smith reported to us last Saturday.
你说他伏身在车把上?
You describe him as bending low over the handle bar?
是的 低伏着
Yes, quite low.
又是为了隐藏面目
Thus concealment again,
对藏那么远的你来说很有效
which in your case worked perfectly.
你做得非常糟糕
Oh know, you really have done remarkably badly.
他走进庄园
He goes back to the Hall
你却一路跑回伦敦
and you come all the way back to London
去找房屋经纪人
to call on a house agent.
我查到了想要的信息
Well, I found the information I was seeking.
你找到个叫威廉森的名字
You found the name Williamson,
对我来说毫无用处
which conveys nothing to my mind.
我们得知他年老以及正派
Well, we know he's elderly and respectable.
因此 不可能是那位精力充沛
And therefore, unlikely to be the energetic cyclist
能快速逃开矫健年轻女孩的骑车人
that sprints away from that athletic young girl.
那我该怎么做?
Well, what should I have done?
去最近的小酒馆
Gone to the nearest public house.
那儿是乡村流言蜚语的中心
That is the center of country gossip.
他们会告诉你庄园内
They would have given you every name
从主人到帮厨女佣的名字
from the master to the scullery maid.
而不是你告诉我的...威廉森
Instead of which, you give me-Williamson.
从你的远行中我们得知
So, what have we gained by your expedition.
那女孩所讲的是真事
The fact that the girl's story is true;
这我从未怀疑
I never doubted that.
骑车人和庄园有关联
That there is a connection between the cyclist and the Hall;
这我也从未怀疑过
I never doubted that, either.
庄园租给一个叫威廉森的人
The Hall is tenanted by a man called Williamson.
谁敢保证就是他?
Who is the better for that?
我明天就去小酒馆
I shall go back tomorrow and visit the public house.
不 不要草率行事
No, my dear sir, do not commit yourself to rashness
因为你暂时很消沉
because you are temporarily depressed.
星期六前做任何事都是徒劳
We can do nothing useful until Saturday.
我真的做得很糟糕?
Did I really do remarkably badly?
没错
Yes.
非常美
Very beautiful.
谢谢 卡拉瑟斯先生
Thank you, Mr. Carruthers.
这是首新曲子
It is a new piece.
我得多加练习
I need to practice it more.
我不是指音乐
No, I don't mean the music.
维尔莉特 我有个问题想问你
Violet, I have a question to ask you.
早上好 福尔摩斯
Morning, Holmes.
维尔莉特・史密斯小姐的来信
A letter from Miss Violet Smith.
卡拉瑟斯向她求婚了
Now Carruthers has proposed marriage to her.
卡拉瑟斯!
Carruthers!
男士有求婚的权利 华生
Gentlemen are permitted to propose marriage, Watson.
他一定不知道西里尔
Of course he didn't know about Cyril.
你要去法恩罕?
Are you going to Farnham?
我想去验证我的一两个设想
I want to test one or two theories which I have formed.
我要一起去吗?
Shall I come with you?
不用 那样既无用又多余
No, that will be neither useful nor necessary.
去最近的小酒馆
Try the nearest public house,
那儿是乡村流言蜚语的中心
always a good center for country gossip.
谢谢 华生 很好的提议!
Thank you, Watson, capital notion!
下午好 店主
Ah, Good afternoon, Landlord.
麻烦能来半品脱当地啤酒吗?
May I have half a pint of your local ale, please?
当然可以 先生
Certainly, sir.
给      谢谢
Here you are.        Thank you.
零钱你留着吧
You may keep the change.
您非常慷慨 先生 但不行
That's most generous of you, sir, but I couldn't.
我没理由接受您的慷慨给予
I haven't done anything to warrant such generosity.
我正打算给你一个理由
I'm about to give you the opportunity.
我需要一些信息
I need some information.
我不爱瞎扯淡 先生
Oh, I'm not one for idle gossip, sir.
我也是 我更喜欢事实
Neither am I, I prefer facts.
跟我谈谈查灵顿庄园的人
Tell me about the people at Charlington Hall.
你是指威廉森先生吗 先生?
You mean Mr. Williamson, sir?
是的
Yes.
他...他刚走不到五分钟
Well, he-he was in here not more than five minutes ago.
你们错过了
You just missed him.
跟我说说这个威廉森先生
Tell me about Mr. Williamson.
他是位年老及正派的绅士吗?
Is he an elderly, respectable gentleman?
他上年纪了 这毫无疑问
Oh, he's elderly, no doubt.
我决不会在背后说人坏话
Far be it from me to speak ill of people behind their backs,
但我不确定他是否为人正派
but I'm none too sure about respectable.
是吗?
Really?
据说他以前是位牧师
He is an ex-clergymen, I reckon.
以前?
Ex?
似乎是
Apparently.
他被除名了
He was struck off,
或什么牧师会有的处分
or whatever it is happens to clergymen.
医生才会被除名
That's doctors that are struck off.
跟我说说庄园里的其他人
Tell me about the other people up at the house.
他们都是家仆
Well, they're just domestic staff,
都是虔诚的本地人
and they're all local and God-fearing.
当然
Of course.
周末总会有一帮人聚集在庄园
He do have folk up there at weekends.
周末?      是的 先生
Weekends?        Yes, sir.
周末
Weekends.
没问题 什么样的人?
Ah, no problem. What sort of folk?
热情的一帮人
Oh, they're a warm lot.
热情?
Warm?
是的 热情得让人
Yes, the sort you won't want to get too near
不敢接近
for fear of getting burnt like.
很好
That's good.
你也许认为好 先生
Oh, you may think it's good, sir.
他们和村里人相处得不太好
They don't come down well in the village, I can tell you.
其中一个人尤为特别
There was one fellow in particular.
特别热情 是吧?
Particularly warm, is he, this fellow?
他非常特别 先生
He is very particularly, sir.
我打赌他蓄着红胡子
I'll wager he has a red mustache.
你认识他吗?
Hey, do you know him?
素未谋面
I never met the gentleman.
那你现在有机会了
Well, now is your chance.
伍德利先生
Mr. Woodley.
关你屁事!
None of your damn business!
店主开了如此体面的酒馆
Our Landlord keeps a very respectable house,
不是你撒泼的地方
and your language is not welcome.
你以为你是谁?
Who do you think you are?
你跑来问东问西
What the hell do you want
到底想干什么?
coming here asking all them questions?
你说得很对 店主 他明显不是君子
You're quite right, Landlord, clearly not a gentleman.
彼此彼此
Oh, I'm as much a gentleman as you are.
在场所有人证明
Everybody here will bear witness to the fact
我是正当自卫
that I am acting in self-defense.
卑鄙小人!
Swine!
不 先生 是君子!
No, sir, a gentleman!
只有恶棍才会用手背打人
Only a ruffian deals a blow with the back of a hand.
而君子 则用左直拳
A gentleman uses the straight-left...
所以先生 我是位君子!
and I, sir, am a gentleman!
有趣极了 华生
It was absolutely delicious, Watson.
看出来了
So I see.
左直拳对抗乱舞的恶棍
A straight left against a slogging ruffian.
我挂彩了
I emerged, as you see.
乱舞的恶棍呢?
And the slogging ruffian?
伍德利先生用马车抬回去了
Mr. Woodley was taken home in a cart.
又是那个可怕的男人
There's that horrible man again.
哪个男人?
Which man?
我今天好像见到伍德利先生在花园里
I thought I saw Mr. Woodley in the garden today.
是的 他住在这附近
You did. He's staying in the area.
但别担心 我郑重地告诫他
But do not worry, I have told him quite firmly
再也不许踏进这座房子
he's not to set foot inside the house.
"亲爱的福尔摩斯先生
"Dear Mr. Holmes:
你一定已经料到
You will not be surprised to learn
我星期六将会辞去
that I will be leaving
卡拉瑟斯先生的那份工作"
Mr. Carruthers's employment on Saturday. "
可恶的伍德利先生又出现在奇尔顿农庄
The odious Mr. Woodley has reappeared at Chiltern Grange.
但起码这次她不用骑车去车站了
Ah, but at least she won't be bicycling to the station.
终于 富有的卡拉瑟斯先生
So finally, the rich Mr. Carruthers
找到马和马车了
has acquired a horse and trap.
的确
Yes.
看这 "一切烦恼将在星期六烟消云散"
Look here, "all my troubles will be over on Saturday. "
明天 福尔摩斯
Tomorrow, Holmes,
她的一切烦恼将会烟消云散
all her troubles will be over.
为什么我对那词感到不安
Why do I worry about that word.
哪个词?
Which word?
"马车"(亦有"陷阱"的意思)
"Trap. "
啊 多么美好的早晨 福尔摩斯!
Oh, what a splendid morning, Holmes!
在这个季节这天气尚算可以
It's acceptable weather for the time of year.
谁会在这么个早晨伤害那可爱的女孩?
Now who would want to harm that dear girl on such a morning?
希望没人会
I hope nobody.
那你怎么带着左轮枪?
So why did you bring your revolver?
我说的是希望 而不是推论
I'm talking about my hope, not my expectations.
怎么?
What?
我想那位是史密斯小姐
I fancy that is our Miss Smith.
她肯定想赶更早一班车
She must be traveling by an earlier train.
我只提前了半个小时
I give her a margin of half an hour,
但在我们会她前
but she'll be past Charlington Hall
她肯定早经过查灵顿庄园了
before we can possibly meet her.
那怎么办好?
So what can we do?
用跑的
We could run.
笨蛋 我早该想到提前出发这点!
Fool, I should have allowed for that earlier train!
是绑架
It's abduction,
华生 是绑架 谋杀 天知道怎么回事
Watson, it's abduction, murder, heaven knows what.
截停那马
Stop that horse.
太好了
Good man.
快来 华生!
Come on, Watson!
看看还能不能亡羊补牢!
Let's see if I can repair the consequences of my own blunder!
那里!
Up there!
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
你们在哪找到的马车?
Where did you get that cart?!
维尔莉特・史密斯小姐在哪?
Where is Miss Violet Smith?!
这话该我问 这是她的马车!
That's what I'm asking you. You were in her cart!
马车在路上 上面一个人也没有!
It was on the road, there was no one in it!
似乎有人从这里走过!
Somebody seems to have gone through this way!
我们得找到他们!
We must find them!
来 华生
Come, Watson.
看 你认识他吗?
Now look, do you know who this is?!
彼得 马夫
That's Peter, the groom,
他送她上车站
he was taking her to the station.
他还活着 脉搏很有力
He's alive, his pulse is strong.
肯定是刚发生的事
Mustn't be left lying there too long.
别管他 不用我们救他
Let him lie, we can't do him any good,
但我们可以从一个女人会遭受
but we might save her from the worst fate
的最坏厄运中救出她
that can befall a woman.
你去哪儿?!
Where are you going?!
大宅!
The house!
他们没去大宅!
They didn't go to the house!
他们走了左边这条路
They went this way to the left.
你肯定?
Are you sure?
卑鄙小人!
Oh, cowardly dogs!
来不及了!      华生
Too late!        Watson.
他们强来 来不及了!
Too late by the living Jingo!
在上帝及其仆人的见证下
For as much as John and Violet
约翰和维尔莉特自愿
have consented together in holy wedlock,
缔结神圣的夫妻关系
and have witnessed the same before God and this company...
并且双方已经
and have declared the same
交换戒指
by the giving and receiving of a ring,
携手终老
and the joining of hands,
我宣布 你们结为夫妻
I pronounce that they be man and wife, together.
恭喜你们!
Congratulations!
谢谢 阿门
Thanks, amen.
他们结婚了!
They're married!
欢迎参加婚宴 先生们
Welcome to the party, gentlemen.
容我介绍伍德利太太
Let me introduce you to Mrs. Woodley.
不要 卡拉瑟斯!
Don't Carruthers!
卡拉瑟斯?
Carruthers!
是的 我要这姑娘安然无恙
Yes, and I'll see this woman righted,
即使为此上绞架也在所不惜
if I have to swing for it.
太迟了
You're too late.
她是我的妻子!
She is my wife!
不 她是你的寡妻
No, she's your widow.
我说过 如果你再骚扰她 我会怎么做!
I told you what I'd do if you molested her!
上帝为证 我言出必行!
By the Lord, I'm a man of my word!
你们雇我的时候
When you hired me,
可没说会发生这些乱七八糟的事!
nobody told me there'd be any of this damn nonsense!
把枪放下
Drop that pistol.
华生 拣起来!
Watson, pick it up!
把枪给我 不要再动武了
Give me that revolver, we'll have no more violence.
你是谁 在这指手画脚?
Who are you to be giving these orders?
夏洛克・福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
天啊
Good Lord.
你!
Here, you!
先生?
Sir?
你还能驾车到法恩罕吗?
Are you well enough to drive into Farnham?
是的 先生 我想可以
Yes, sir, I reckon I am.
把这张纸条
Then give this note
交给警察局局长
to the superintendent of the police station.
现在
In the meantime,
你们都受我的监管
I must detain you all under my own personal custody.
俩病人怎么样 医生?
How are the patients, Doctor?
史密斯小姐很好
Miss Smith's very well,
尽管受到如此恶劣的对待
considering the foul way she's been treated.
伍德利呢?
And Woodley?
唉 他还活着
Alas, I have no doubt he will live.
什么 那我上楼去结果他
What, I'll go upstairs and finish him off.
不 坐下 卡拉瑟斯
No, sit down in that chair, Carruthers.
你是对的
You're right.
他不值得我为他送死
He isn't worth swinging for.
但难道那姑娘真的得
But do you tell me that girl
一辈子受狂徒伍德利的束缚吗?
is to be tied to Roaring Jack Woodley for life?!
用不着你过问
You needn't concern yourself about that.
我主持了婚礼 他们至死不渝
I married them till death do them part.
她不可能成为他妻室
Under no circumstances can she be considered his wife.
你确定?
Are you sure?
原因有二
For two very good reasons.
第一 我们完全可以
In the first place, we are very safe in
质疑威廉森先生
questioning Mr. Williamson's right
主持婚礼的资格
to solemnize a marriage.
我受任过圣职
I have been ordained.
已被免去圣职
And unfrocked.
一朝为牧师 终身为牧师
Once a clergyman, always a clergyman.
我不这么看
I think not.
那结婚证呢?
How about the license?
我们有结婚证
Oh, we had a license.
在这儿
I have it here.
无疑是用不法手段取得的
Undoubtedly obtained by a trick.
但无论如何 强迫的婚姻不是婚姻
But, in any case, a forced marriage is no marriage,
而你会发现 这是一项重罪
indeed, it is a very serious felony, as you will discover.
在等警察的这段时间里 卡拉瑟斯先生
Now, while we are waiting for the police, Mr. Carruthers,
说说你的事
you might tell me your story.
如果你把秘密捅出去 鲍・卡拉瑟斯
If you squeal on us, Bob Carruthers,
我会像你对付杰克・伍德利那样对付你
I'll serve you as you served Jack Woodley!
你不用瞎激动
There's no need for you to get over-excited.
事情再清楚不过了
The case is clear enough.
既然你那么清楚 为什么不由你来说
Well, if it's clear enough, why don't you tell us.
很好
Very well.
卡拉瑟斯先生得适当补充细节
Mr. Carruthers will have to fill in a few details
以满足我个人的好奇心
for my private curiosity,
但我很乐意来讲述
but I am happy to do the talking.
首先
In the first place,
你们三个从南非来
the three of you came across from South Africa.
错了 我从没去过南非!
Wrong, I've never even been in South Africa!
是真的
It's true.
伍德利在我们回来后才找到这禽兽
Woodley acquired this creature after our return.
很好 你和伍德利
Very well, you and Woodley
在南非结识了拉夫・史密斯
had known Ralph Smith in South Africa.
你们相信他将不久于人世
You had reason to believe that he would not live long,
并发现他侄女将继承他的遗产
and you found out that his niece would inherit his fortune.
没错吧?
How's that?
你们却告诉她 她叔叔死时贫困交加
But you told the girl her uncle died in poverty.
因为他明显奄奄一息
Well, as he was still alive, admittedly only just,
我想这有钱人没立下遗嘱
and a wealthy man who I suspect had made no will.
拉夫・史密斯不认字也不会写
Ralph Smith could neither read nor write.
因此你和伍德利回来寻找他侄女
So, you and Woodley came over here and hunted up the girl,
得知维尔莉特是他最亲的人
knowing she was the next of kin,
你们可以分掉遗产
and that you would share the plunder.
作为公证费 我也可以分得一份
I was due a share for services rendered.
而卡拉瑟斯
And Carruthers,
你却犯了个错误
you made the mistake
爱上了她
of falling in love with her.
生平第一次知道什么叫爱 福尔摩斯先生
The first time that ever I knew what love was, Mr. Holmes.
为什么你不告诉她她的危险处境?
Why didn't you tell her of the danger she was in?
因为...
Because-
因为这样她会离开我
Because she would have left me,
我受不了这样
and I couldn't bear to face that.
我的女儿莎拉怎么办?
Oh, what will happen to my daughter, Sarah?
她会得到妥善照顾的
We'll see she's well taken care of.
尽管她不会爱上我
You see, even if she couldn't love me,
但能在房子里见到她
it meant a great deal to see her about the house
听到她的声音 我就知足了
and hear the sound of her voice.
你称之为爱 卡拉瑟斯先生
You may call it love, Mr. Carruthers,
我却称之为自私
I should call it selfishness.
也许两者是共存的
Maybe the two things go together.
但我想保护她
But I tried to protect her,
我从未让她
I never once let her go past this house
独自经过这座
where I knew those rascals were lurking
流氓潜伏的房子
without following her on my bicycle
我会亲眼看着她不受伤害
to see she came to no harm.
我保持距离并戴上假胡子
I kept my distance and wore that beard
这样她就不会认出我
so she should not recognize me.
然后我想你收到了电报?
Then I presume the cable arrived?
电报 什么电报?
Cable, what cable?
"老儿已死"
"THE OLD MAN IS DEAD."
哪个老儿?
What old man?
我想是在南非的拉夫・史密斯
I imagine Ralph Smith in South Africa.
是的
Yes.
但此时你和伍德利吵了一架
But by this time you and Woodley had quarreled
然后他离开了农庄
and he had left the house.
伍德利又来问我是否依原计划行事
Woodley came back again to ask me to stick to the bargain.
我拒绝了
I refused.
我说我不会使用武力
I said I would have nothing to do with violence.
最后一个细节
One last detail,
为什么由伍德利来充当丈夫?
why was Woodley chosen as the prospective husband?
这让我难以启齿...
I am ashamed to say it...
我们打牌 拿她做赌注
we played cards for her.
福尔摩斯 我知道判决结果了
Holmes, I have the results of the trial.
听着 法官总结说...
Listen to this, the judge in summing up said-
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
华生 我能否凭经验猜测?
Watson, may I be permitted an educated guess?
说吧
Go on then.
我想伍德利会被判刑10年
I would expect Woodley to get ten years,
威廉森7年
Williamson seven years,
至于卡拉瑟斯
and Carruthers,
鉴于审判时
in view of the eloquent speech
我为他作的一番出色辩解
I made on his behalf at the trial,
大约6个月吧
probably six months.
丝毫不差!
That is exactly right!
我有些优势 华生
Well, I have certain advantages, Watson,
大部分数据来源于更早出版的报纸
largely the fact that I sent out for the early edition.
的确是优势
An undoubted advantage.
同时 我们收到了一份礼物
Also, we have received a present,
来自西里尔・莫尔顿夫妇的结婚蛋糕
some wedding cake from Mr. and Mrs. Cyril Morton,
随之附了一封信说
together with a letter telling us
莫尔顿太太早前在南非的叔叔
that Mrs. Morton has inherited a large sum of money
拉夫・史密斯处继承了一大笔遗产
from her uncle, Ralph Smith, formerly of South Africa.
这对幸福的夫妇很乐意
The happy couple are thoroughly enjoying
在其父亲服刑期间
looking after young Sarah Carruthers,
照顾莎拉・卡拉瑟斯
while her father is in custody.
她的琴艺正不断进步
Her piano playing is improving
并且想学骑车
and she wants to take up bicycling.
到处都过着美好的日子 不是吗?
A splendid day all round, wouldn't you say?
还有更好的事要发生
There is more splendor yet to come.
更好的事 什么意思?
More splendor, what do you mean?
仔细看
Watch carefully.
哦 我想起来了
Oh, I remember,
将解决约翰・文森特・哈登先生
the chemical reaction that will solve the mystery
迫害事件中疑点的化学反应
concerning the persecution of Mr. John Vincent Harden.
没错
Precisely.
我在皇家科学博物馆泡了一个星期
I've spent the entire week in the Imperial Science Museum
我想这就是答案
and I think this is the answer.
那就是答案 福尔摩斯?
Is that the answer, Holmes?
没错 那就是答案 华生
Yes, that is the answer, Watson.
让我再想想
Well, let me think.